so as everyone knows I treat middle-age
and older men I don't treat men under 30
unless they have true hypogonadism and
there's a couple reasons for that it's
just that there's so many older men that
need it that don't know it I treat a lot
of men with prostate cancer and and
other issues so I treat men basically 40
and above yes I have some in their 30s
but but for the most part it's a it's an
older age group 40 and above and what I
do is biodental hormone replacement
therapy now there's testosterone
replacement therapy which is a
testosterone itself which may be
adequate for many men in their teens and
20s of course but when you get above 40
it becomes about biod denal hormone
replacement therapy meaning that we're
addressing all the hormones and we're
trying to address the age related
decline that occurs in all of us it's
about prevention of age related disease
disability dependence and Frailty it's
about never suffering the symptoms of a
deficiency it really is about prevention
but prevention is a hard concept Dave
because we've all been Tau from a very
young age we only go to the doctor we
only go when we're sick when we feel ill
we don't go when we feel good we we're
not taught about prevention but what
this is really about is about prevention
I was listening to a lecture a very good
cancer specialist a year or two ago and
he pointed out that look these cancer
cells when you get diagnosed with cancer
in your 60s or 70s it didn't develop
last year or even two years ago it
started developing decades before so
what some of these men start doing and
they're late 30s basically 40 and above
is going to make a significant impact on
their health and well-being decades down
the road so we don't wait for these
older men 40 and above to get symptoms
of a deficiency we're preventing the
symptoms of the deficiency from ever
developing and that's really what it's
about it's understanding that each and
every hormone has beneficial effects but
they work
synergistically now that's a little
different sometimes and we don't give
contradictory advice we we are basically
we're on the same page in literally
every facet so it kind of differs in the
advice that you give these younger men
that are less than 30 so why don't you
talk to us about how you kind of
approach that age group of men says
that's not my age population that I
treat sure absolutely I I I like the way
that you look at um hormone replacement
from just to touch on what you said and
the way that I I use the analogy is that
we again I'm coming back to cars all the
time but we know that if your car needs
a service if you keep driving it you're
going to make the problem worse and if
you know the wheels are going to fly off
and you know you don't need to wait for
a massive crisis to happen before you go
to the mechanic you go earlier to
prevent the bill from being huge but in
this case we're not talking about a bill
for your car we're talking about your
health you only get one body so I really
like this approach of focusing on
longevity through hormone optimization
because you're protecting against the
diseases of Aging which are basically
left to manifest it leaves the body wide
open which is what we particularly it's
not not what we but it's what the
medical industry has been much better at
identifying in women in menopause all
their diseases of Aging risk goes
through the roof and one thing that we
know for sure well I would hope most
people know for sure I know that you at
tier one do because you your wife treats
women you don't just treat one hormone
in menopause um and it's the same with
age related hormone decline in men um
it's not just testosterone just like
it's not just progesterone in women it's
it's all hormones that go down and it
there's smoke there's fire so if you're
old enough to have low testosterone from
age there is a very good chance unless
you're an outlier that you have also
begun to decline in other hormones it
just wouldn't make sense otherwise I
guess the thing that's different when
and and I I also treat older men and I
treat older men very similarly to how Dr
Keith Nichols does um but when I treat
younger men it's a little bit different
because they're not dealing with age
related hormone decline they're dealing
with what I believe or sometimes it's
just poor diet and lifestyle but a lot
of the time we're getting these younger
guys who are coming up who were 21 22
they're healthy they're doing everything
right to to the point that it's almost a
bit weird they're doing everything
perfectly and they've got lower
testosterone levels than you'd see in
the average 65 to 70 year old and I
think this is a result of endocrine
disruption potentially unhealthy parents
exposure to all there's so many
different things it's the perfect storm
but I haven't found that those things
are impacting the levels of DHEA
sometimes thyroid actually thyroids very
common but the adrenal hormones like
pregnant alone and DHEA I haven't found
to be too impacted in these younger men
I mean when you get these guys come in
with these really low levels of
testosterone sometimes they have even
above range levels of DHEA naturally
because they're 21 that's where they're
meant to be um but it would be very rare
to get to it get to the age of let's say
50 years old and have low testosterone
and have robust levels of these other
hormones it would be very very rare so
that's the the difference that we're
talking about here and one of the things
that I think is a bit of a myth in the
space and this is where people probably
think we're going to have a debate and
an argument but in fact we're just going
to agree on it is that a lot of the time
these younger guys think that going on
testosterone replacement therapy is
causing their low pregnant alone and
DHEA levels because they've disrupted
this system and while it does reduce the
levels in the testicles or in the
ovaries in in in a woman when we're
looking at The Knockout of lutenizing
hormone activity the thing that that Dr
Keith Nichols has picked up very well
and and it's why it's so important
actually referred a gentleman over to
Keith uh this week who came to me who
was on trt but he was in his 60s and the
other hormones hadn't been addressed yet
I was like this is exactly what Keith
talks about is that once you get to that
age the Synergy between the hormones is
so important and I like to kind of when
Keith talks about how some of these
hormones you feel some of them you don't
I refer them a little bit differently
kind of similar I look at hormones like
testosterone DHEA and thyroid as
accelerators and things like
pregnanolone and melatonin as the brakes
and if you've got a deficiency in your
brakes and accelerators and you come in
and crank up one accelerator you've now
created a bigger discrepancy between all
these hormones you've created further
you've fixed a problem but now you've
created more because you've got further
imbalance and that's why it's so
important but not only just is it
important from like a pragmatic
standpoint but from an outcome
standpoint if you take a gentleman who's
deficient in all these hormones and you
just put testosterone in there he'll
come in and think oh testosterone is
going to fix all my problems because
it's sounds cool it's marketable it's we
it's like selling a thirsty guy a glass
of water everyone wants more
testosterone but in reality it's
pregnant alone DHEA thyroid melatonin Al
together that actually do what guys are
hoping testosterone will do well well
said I I tell my middle-age and older
men that look when they come in Dave
they have you as you just made the
statement they they're all in on
testosterone all in hey some most of
them you know hey the more the better
but they're all in onest testosterone
and I tell these men that look the way
you win this mind game this battle
between your ears is that you need to
approach every one of those hormones as
you do
testosterone the better the levels the
better the benefits that's what this is
all about we're trying to obtain optimal
levels so that you obtain more benefit
from each hormone and at the same time
balance that against any unwanted side
effects and so that's really the point
that I get and men will say well I've
Been Told that you know I don't need
these other hormones especially if I got
normal levels and they're at 40 50 60
years old you realize that the normal
levels for 4050 and 60 year old man for
like DHE for instance is a lot lower
than the normal range for a 22 year old
man that's over 400 so the goals of what
we're doing is maintaining these levels
as you age in your 40s 50s and 60s just
as they were when you were in your 20s
so an optimal level and I'll ask those
men so you're okay with testosterone yep
that's what I want will your levels are
normal why do you want testosterone if
your levels are normal well because I've
I've read that it didn't matter if
they're normal I still I can still have
problems well that is correct you read
that correct but yet you're willing to
start testosterone at your age with a
normal level but you're not willing to
start any of your other hormones
foundational hormones because you have
normal levels that doesn't make sense to
me and the reason is is because you know
the two feel-good hormones the two that
you can really base on symptomatic
Improvement of course they going to be
thyroid and testosterone you know could
literally base my adjustments really on
on on on clinical symptomatology and
Improvement a lot of those other
hormones Dave uh you know like the DHE
the pregalin alone vitamin D3 for
instance look we really don't notice it
when we take it for the most part now
look let's make sure we we kind of set
the grounds rules right here real quick
Dave and I'm going to make a point by
asking just a few simple questions Dave
can you take Tylenol without any
problems sorry what's the generic name
for Tylenol we don't call it Ty can I
take it without any problems yeah in the
short term yeah me too okay can you take
uh Advil ibuprofen in the short term
yeah yeah yeah and so you know so you
can literally take certain medications
over the counter medications without any
problems at all right yes now remember
there's gonna be people out there that
are going to say I can't take Tylenol it
makes me sick it gives me a headache I
can't do it I can't take Ibuprofen makes
me sick does this out or other I can't
take you know benad
look when we talk to these men about
these hormones we are talking to the
95.9 or 99.5% of people that can
tolerate it everybody out there when
they hear a video like you or mine oh I
can't take dhu oh yeah when I take DH I
know it it just that's okay I'm that's
good to know but the majority of us
can't tell it especially 40 and above
when we take these hormones like vitamin
D3 now you can know when you're vitamin
D3 deficient when it's been a long time
yes it can cause fatigue and other
issues but the point is is that I'm
really trying to make is that we're not
speaking to you guys that are those
so-called 1% outliers that feel it when
you take it or or just have all kinds of
issues when you take it the majority of
us and when you look at the studies and
older men and women that do take these
hormones they don't have really many
problems with it all right so so the
point is is that so these other hormones
since they don't have tremendous
feel-good effects we do try to optimize
levels and that's when we do maybe aim
for levels uh with these other hor
hormones whereas testosterone and
thyroid I'm not aiming for a level I'm
treating for symptomatic Improvement so
I just wanted to make the distinction
there and that they they understand why
we do what we do and so the majority of
us can take these without any problems
but if you can't take it if you can't
tolerate it then either take it in a
lower dose or don't take it at all let's
don't make something that should be very
simple more complicated than it is we're
using biodental hormones you are an
advocate for as as we all should be
micronized sustained or loose
pharmaceutical grade hormones they work
the best you've said it over and over
again you've done a great job and all
your information so I just want to make
sure that people do understand that
that's what we're doing with hormone
optimization especially in my age group
we're preventing age related decline
we're maximizing levels to maximize
benefits there's a dose response
relationship that's all it is Danielle
ruser my my good friend and colleague
Mentor uh as he says he wants his on his
grave he wants it to say what do you
want your levels to be that's all he
want us to say what do you want your
levels to be so I'll always ask men
these are what the hormones do what
would you want your levels to be I can
make them low so you get low effects of
the hormone I can give you mid-range
levels and you can have mid-range
effects or I can give you an optimal
level so that you can maximize those
benefits of that hormone which would you
like oh doc I want I want to maximize it
so that's kind of my our our take that's
what hormone optimization is in in our
world it's just it's just that it's not
complicated it shouldn't be complicated
uh we'll talk about all these other
add-ons a lot of other clinics want to
do you know you send an email to me
whether be HCG and these other things
and uh so it's just uh it just doesn't
need to be complicated you've identified
just how simple it should be and it
is